website: willtownes.github.io email: ftownes@andrew.cmu.edu

CONTACT	
Information	n

Department of Statistics and Data Science Carnegie Mellon University

Pittsburgh, PA USA

#### SUMMARY

I am an applied statistician working primarily with biomedical data. I am involved with infectious disease as part of the Delphi Group and have developed methods for spatial and single-cell genomics. I am also interested in wearable devices, ecology, and economics. I strive to produce open source software implementations to help scientists achieve their research goals more effectively.

Professional
EXPERIENCE

2022 - present	Assistant Professor, Department of Statistics and Data Science	
	Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA	
2019 - 2022	Postdoctoral Researcher, Department of Computer Science	
	Princeton University, Princeton, NJ (advisor: Barbara Engelhardt)	
2011 - 2014	Software Test Engineer, SRA International, Arlington, VA	
2008 - 2010	Software Analyst, Perrin Quarles Associates, Charlottesville, VA	
2007 - 2008	Fulbright Scholar, University of the Philippines	
	Conducted independent forest ecology research while living with an	
	indigenous Aeta community in Bataan Province.	

## EDUCATION

2019 Ph.D. Biostatistics, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA USA

Dissertation Committee: Rafael Irizarry (Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Data Science)

Jeff Miller (Harvard University, Biostatistics)

Martin Aryee (Massachusetts General Hospital, Pathology)

2013 M.S. Mathematics & Statistics, Georgetown University, Washington, DC USA

2007 B.S. Biology, Washington & Lee University, Lexington, VA USA

## Research II

## In Review

- [1] Jones A, **Townes FW**, Li D, Engelhardt BE. Alignment of spatial genomics and histology data using deep Gaussian processes (2022). Preprint: doi:10.1101/2022.01.10.475692.
- [2] **Townes FW**, Engelhardt BE. Nonnegative spatial factorization (2021). Preprint: https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.06122.
- [3] Verpeut JL, Bergeler S, Kislin M, **Townes FW**, Klibaite U, Dhanerawala ZM, Hoag A, Jung C, Lee J, Pisano TJ, Seagraves KM, Shaevitz JW, Wang SSH. Cerebellar contributions to a brainwide network for flexible behavior (2021). Preprint: doi:10.1101/2021.12.07.471685.

# In Press

[1] Gewirtz ADH, **Townes FW**, and Engelhardt BE. Telescoping bimodal latent Dirichlet allocation to identify expression QTLs across tissues *Life Science Alliance* (2021). Preprint: doi:10.1101/2021.10.27.466156.

# Peer-reviewed Journal Articles

- [1] Jones A, **Townes FW**, Li D, Engelhardt BE. Contrastive latent variable modeling with application to case-control sequencing experiments. *Annals of Applied Statistics* (2022). doi:10.1214/21-AOAS1534.
- [2] Hecker J, Townes FW, Kachroo P, Lasky-Su J, Ziniti J, Cho MH, Weiss ST, Laird NM, Lange C. A unifying framework for rare variant association testing in family-based designs, including higher criticism approaches, SKATs, and burden tests. *Bioinformatics* (2020). doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btaa1055.
- [3] **Townes FW**, Carr K, Miller JW. Identifying longevity associated genes by integrating gene expression and curated annotations. *PLOS Computational Biology* (2020). doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1008429.

- [4] **Townes FW**, Irizarry RA. Quantile normalization of single-cell RNA-seq read counts without unique molecular identifiers. *Genome Biology* (2020). doi:10.1186/s13059-020-02078-0.
- [5] Townes FW, Hicks SC, Aryee MJ, Irizarry RA. Feature selection and dimension reduction for single-cell RNA-Seq based on a multinomial model. *Genome Biology* (2019). doi:10.1186/s13059-019-1861-6.
- [6] Marsh DM, Townes FW, Cotter K, Farroni K, McCreary K, Petry R, Tilghman J. Thermal Preference and Species Range in Mountaintop Salamanders and Their Widespread Competitors. *Journal of Herpetology* (2019). doi:10.1670/18-110.
- [7] Hicks SC, **Townes FW**, Teng M, Irizarry RA. Missing Data and Technical Variability in Single-Cell RNA-Sequencing Experiments. *Biostatistics* (2018). doi:10.1101/025528.
- [8] Hecker, J, Xu X, **Townes FW**, Fier HL, Corcoran C, Laird N, Lange C. Family-Based Tests for Associating Haplotypes With General Phenotype Data: Application to Asthma Genetics. *Genetic Epidemiology* (2017). doi:10.1002/gepi.22094.
- [9] Valeri L, Patterson-Lomba O, Gurmu Y, Ablorh A, Bobb J, Townes FW, Harling G. Predicting Subnational Ebola Virus Disease Epidemic Dynamics from Sociodemographic Indicators. *PLOS One* (2016). doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0163544.
- [10] **Townes W**. Seed dispersal of the genus Leea in forest patches of Bataan, Philippines. *Ecotropica* (2010).

## Technical Reports

- [1] **Townes FW**. Review of Probability Distributions for Modeling Count Data. arXiv (2020). https://arxiv.org/abs/2001.04343.
- [2] **Townes FW**. Generalized Principal Component Analysis. *arXiv* (2019). https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.02647.

#### Talks Invited

- [1] Advanced Biomedical Computation Seminar, Computational Pathology Department, Brigham and Women's Hospital. March 2022.
- [2] Statistics and Data Science Department, Carnegie Mellon University. March 2022.
- [3] Biomedical Data Science Department, Stanford University. February 2022.
- [4] Biostatistics Department, University of Michigan. January 2022.
- [5] Population and Public Health Sciences Department, University of Southern California. January 2022.
- [6] Emerging Concepts in Microbial Informatics, Molecular Medicine and Biotechnology (panelist). Trinity University of Asia. November 2021.
- [7] Don't Normalize: the GLM-PCA approach to normalization. *Normjam*, New York Genome Center. November 2019.
- [8] Biostatistics and Data Science as a Career Path. Biology Department, Washington & Lee University. October 2019.

## Contributed Talks

- [1] Latent factorization methods for genomics. New England Statistical Symposium (virtual presenter). May 2022.
- [2] Nonnegative process factorization for multivariate spatial count data. *Joint Statistical Meetings* (virtual conference). August 2021.

- [3] Quantile normalization of single-cell RNA-seq read counts without unique molecular identifiers. Joint Statistical Meetings (virtual conference). August 2020.
- [4] Dimension reduction for massive single-cell datasets. *Bioconductor Annual Meeting* (virtual conference). July 2020. slides doi:10.7490/f1000research.1118084.1
- [5] Dimension Reduction for Single Cell RNA-Seq based on a Multinomial Model. *Joint Statistical Meetings* (Denver, CO). August 2019.
- [6] Varying-Censoring Aware Matrix Factorization for Single Cell RNA-Sequencing. *Bioconductor Annual Meeting* (Boston, MA). July 2017.

#### Seminars

- [1] Human tumor atlas network steering committee meeting. April 2022.
- [2] Nonnegative spatial factorization. Hansen and Hicks labs, Department of Biostatistics, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health. November 2021.
- [3] Primer: Generalized linear models and latent factor models. *Broad Institute Models, Inference, and Algorithms.* October 2020.
- [4] Feature Selection and Dimension Reduction for Single Cell RNA-Seq. Greene Lab, Department of Systems Pharmacology and Translational Therapeutics, Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania. February 2019.
- [5] Unsupervised Learning for Single Cell Gene Expression. *Harvard Biostatistics Cancer Working Group*. September 2018.
- [6] Single Cell Housekeeping Genes and Normalization. Dana-Farber Cancer Institute cBio Seminar. April 2018.
- [7] Informative Missing Data in Single Cell RNA-Seq. Dana-Farber Cancer Institute Genomics Seminar. October 2016.
- [8] Family Based Association Tests for Rare Variants. Brigham & Women's Hospital Channing Network Medicine Seminar. September 2015.

#### Interviews

[1] The Bioinformatics Chat. March 2020. https://bioinformatics.chat/glm-pca

## Posters

- [1] Townes FW, Shukla C. Gene Expression Autoencoders. Harvard Biomedical Informatics 707 (Deep Learning in Healthcare). April 2018.
- [2] Townes FW, Marquez-Luna C. Mixture of Experts Analysis of Infectious Disease Outbreak Characteristics. Harvard Computer Science 281 (Advanced Machine Learning). December 2015.
- [3] Townes FW, Karaayvaz M, Gillespie S, Bernstein B, Ellisen L, Aryee M. Single Cell RNA-Seq Technical and Biological Confounders. Program in Quantitative Genomics Conference, Harvard Medical School. November 2015.

Peer Review **Journals**: American Journal of Human Genetics, Bioinformatics, Biostatistics, Genome Biology, NAR Genomics and Bioinformatics, Nature Communications

Funding

- 2018 2019 NIH T32 Training Grant: Cancer
   2017 Chan-Zuckerberg Foundation Travel Grant
   Human Cell Atlas Jamboree. European Bioinformatics Institute, Hinxton, UK
- 2016 2018 NIH T32 Training Grant: Big Data to Knowledge
  - 2016 NSF-CBMS Travel Award: Topology, Geometry, and Statistics
- 2014 2016 NIH T32 Training Grant: Clinical Epidemiology of Lung Diseases

Professional American Statistical Association, International Society for Computational Biology Societies

TEACHING EXPERIENCE	2021 Fall	Guest lecture, Advanced Computational Genomics (Princeton - COS 597D)
	2020 Fall	Guest lecture, Computational Biology of Single Cells (Princeton - COS 597F)
	2018 Fall	Teaching Assistant, Applied Regression (Harvard - BST 210)
		Grade homeworks, hold office hours, and teach a weekly lab section.
	2018 Summer	Co-Instructor, StatStart (Harvard)
		Statistics program for under-represented high school students.
2017 2017 2016 2016		Gave two interactive lectures on graphing data and regression.
	2017 Fall	Teaching Assistant, Applied Bayesian Analysis (Harvard - BST 228)
		Grade homeworks, provide solutions, and hold office hours.
	2017 Summer	Lead Instructor, Introduction to Data Science (PARSE Ltd.)
		Nonprofit, week-long statistics program for high school students.
		Developed course material and gave interactive lectures using R.
	2017 Spring	Teaching Assistant, Applied Longitudinal Analysis (Harvard - BST 226)
		Grade homeworks and hold office hours.
	2016 Fall	Teaching Assistant, Intro to Statistical Methods (Harvard - BST 201)
		Grade homeworks, provide solutions, hold office hours, and teach a weekly lab section.
	2016 Summer	Project Mentor, Pipelines into Biostatistics (Harvard)
		Program for under-represented undergraduates.
		Guided three students on a pharmacogenomics data analysis.
	2016 Spring	Teaching Assistant, Rates and Proportions (Harvard - BST 210)
	2010 Opinis	Grade homeworks, provide solutions, hold office hours, and teach a weekly lab section.
		Grade nomeworks, provide sordinons, noid office nours, and teach a weekly lab section.

# SOFTWARE PACKAGES

- [1] glmpca: dimension reduction for non-normally distributed data. R package: https://cran.r-project.org/package=glmpca, python package: https://pypi.org/project/glmpca/
- [2] scry: Small-Count Analysis Methods for High-Dimensional Data. Bioconductor R package: https://bioconductor.org/packages/release/bioc/html/scry.html
- [3] **quminorm**: Quantile normalization of non-UMI single cell read counts. R package: https://github.com/willtownes/quminorm
- [4] **spatial-factorization**: Spatially-aware probabilistic factor models. Python package: https://github.com/willtownes/spatial-factorization-py

# TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming: R, Python, SQL, Git, IATEX, Shell Operating Systems: MacOS, Linux, Windows

Machine Learning Frameworks: Caret, Scikit-learn, Keras, Tensorflow, Stan